Finding aid for the Dan Curry papers, 1967-2008 LSC.2294
UCLA Library Special Collections
Dan Curry papers
1967-2008
1987-1991
UCLA Library Special Collections
Curry, Dan
Curry, Ubolvan C.
LSC.2294
7.6 linear feet (12 boxes)
162 audiovisual carriers (72 videocassettes, 90 film strips)
2 linear feet (2 unprocessed boxes)
Dan Curry, born Daniel F. Curry, is an Emmy Award-winning fine artist and filmmaker. He is best known --- and has won seven Emmy awards for --- his work as Visual Effects Producer of Star Trek: The Next Generation, Star Trek: Deep Space Nine, Star Trek: Voyager, and Star Trek: Enterprise. This collection documents Curry's work as visual effects producer of these series, as well as his work on other motion picture and television projects. The bulk of the collection dates from 1987 to 1992, and includes collected screenplays, montage storyboards, memos, recorded material, and Curry's personal notes and hand-drawn illustrations.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed audiovisual materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by Daniel F. Curry and Ubolvan C. Curry in November 2015.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9980578513606533
Biography/History
Dan Curry, born Daniel F. Curry, is an Emmy Award-winning fine artist and filmmaker. Born in New York City in 1946, he graduated from Middlebury College in Vermont with a major in Fine Arts and a minor in Theater. Upon completion of his degree, he joined the Peace Corps and served in Northeast Thailand building small damns and bridges. After his service, he stayed in Asia as a freelance artist where he accepted numerous film, production design, and architectural commissions, a highlight being a commission from the King of Thailand to be a production designer for the Royal Ball.
Upon his return to the United States, Curry worked for a time as a biomedical illustrator and a teacher of fine arts at a small college in New York before attending graduate school at Humboldt State University for a Master's degree in Fine Arts. Upon completion of this degree in the late 1970s, Curry began work in the entertainment industry directing and supervising visual effects, title design, matte painting, and martial arts and weapons design among other elements of the filmmaking process. He is best known – and has won seven Emmy awards for – his work as Visual Effects Producer of Star Trek: The Next Generation, Star Trek: Deep Space Nine, Star Trek: Voyager, and Star Trek: Enterprise. Additionally, he directed an episode of Star Trek: The Next Generation (1993), and occasionally acted in short films and an episode of Star Trek: Deep Space Nine (1993). He continues to work on visual effects for various motion picture and television projects while maintaining an online gallery of his artwork.
Scope and Content
With material dating between 1967 and 2008, this collection documents Dan Curry's work as visual effects producer of several Star Trek series, as well as his work on other motion picture and television projects. The bulk of the collection dates from 1987 to 1992, during which time Curry was first visual effects supervisor, then visual effects producer of Star Trek: The Next Generation. As a result, this collection's strength lies in the screenplays, montage storyboards, and memos collected by Curry as well as his personal notes and hand-drawn illustrations pertaining to this series. The collection also contains similar, although a lesser amount of, material for Star Trek: Deep Space Nine, Star Trek: Voyager, and Star Trek: Enterprise. Most of the recorded material in the collection includes element reels, comp reels, and episode cuts of The Next Generation, but Voyager and Enterprise are also represented. Finally, the collection also consists of scripts, screenplays, and other records documenting Curry's work on various film and television projects.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series primarily by project type, and therein chronologically. Files were given the title of the specific Star Trek episode, motion picture, or television project to which their contents relate. The general arrangement reflects Dan Curry's original order where present. The series and subseries of this collection are organized as follows:
Series 1: Star Trek, circa 1987-2002
Subseries 1.1: Star Trek: The Next Generation, circa 1987-1994
Subseries 1.2: Star Trek: Deep Space Nine, circa 1993-1997
Subseries 1.3: Star Trek: Voyager, circa 1994-2000
Subseries 1.4: Star Trek: Enterprise, circa 2001-2004
Series 2: Star Trek VHS Tapes, circa 1967-2005
Series 3: Motion Picture Projects, circa 1988-1992
Series 4: Television Projects, 1990-2008
Related Material
Joe Menosky papers, 1983-2005, (bulk 1995-2001). Collection Number: 2250.
Gene Roddenberry Star Trek television series collection, 1966-1969. Collection Number: PASC 62.
Robert H. Justman Collection of Star Trek Television Series Scripts, 1966-1968. Collection Number: 89.
Television producers and directors -- United States -- Archives.; Motion picture producers and directors -- United States -- Archives.; Curry, Dan -- Archives; Curry, Dan; Curry, Ubolvan C.
- Series 1: Star Trek, 1987-2002
  Scope and Content
  This series mostly contains scripts annotated by Curry and montage storyboards for several series of Star Trek. Curry also compiled copies of scripts, memos, hand-drawn screenplays, illustrations, and other personal notes on selected episodes into folders he labeled with these episodes' titles. These folders are the highlight of the collection, as they document Curry's creative thought process and the amount of work he put into producing the visual effects for these episodes. Where applicable, multiple folders were created for one file to preserve this arrangement.
  Organization and Arrangement
  This series is arranged in four subseries organized chronologically by Star Trek series and record creation date. Folder titles utilize episode titles and the following popular acronyms for the series: "TNG" for Star Trek: The Next Generation, "DS9" for Star Trek: Deep Space Nine, "VOY" for Star Trek: Voyager, and "ENT" for Star Trek: Enterprise.
  - Subseries 1.1: Star Trek: The Next Generation, 1987-1994
    - TNG: "Haven", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - TNG: "Datalore", circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - TNG: "Too Short a Season", circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - TNG: "When the Bough Breaks", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - TNG: "Home Soil", circa 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - TNG: "Coming of Age", circa 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      Includes one diffusion transfer (Polaroid) print of the matte painting of the "Relva 7." Also contains material on "Home Soil," as included by Dan Curry.
    - TNG: Stock Element Lists, circa 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - TNG: "The Arsenal of Freedom", circa 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - TNG: "We'll Always Have Paris", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - TNG: "Symbiosis", circa 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - TNG: "Conspiracy", circa 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6, Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - TNG: "The Child", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - TNG: "Elementary, Dear Data", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - TNG: "Loud as a Whisper", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - TNG: "Unnatural Selection", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - TNG: "The Measure of a Man", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - TNG: "Where Silence Has Lease", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Includes printed posts on a "Sci-Fi Fantasy Forum" discussing the episode. Praises of the visual and special effects were highlighted before receipt of the collection.
    - TNG: "The Dauphin", 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - TNG: "A Matter of Honor", 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - TNG: "Contagion", 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - TNG: "High Regard", 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - TNG: "Time to the Second", 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - TNG: "Pen Pals", 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - TNG: "Q Who?", 1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - TNG: "The Royale", 1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Contains memos and one montage storyboard (Act 4 missing).
    - TNG: "Samaritan Snare", 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - TNG: "Send in the Clones", 1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - TNG: "Manhunt", 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - TNG: "The Emissary", 1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - TNG: "Peak Performance", 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - TNG: "Shades of Gray", 1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - TNG: Second Season Book O' Shows, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - TNG: "The Bonding", 1989 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - TNG: "The Survivors", 1989 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    - TNG: "The Hunted", 1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - TNG: "Captain's Holiday", 1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - TNG: "Hollow Pursuits", 1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - TNG: "Transfigurations", 1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - TNG: "Family", 1990 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - TNG: "Suddenly Human", 1990 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - TNG: "Future Imperfect", 1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - TNG: "Legacy", 1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - TNG: "Devil's Due", 1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - TNG: "The Wounded", 1990 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - TNG: "The Loss", 1990 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - TNG: "Galaxy's Child", 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - TNG: "Identity Crisis", 1991 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - TNG: "Clues", 1991 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - TNG: "Q Love", 1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - TNG: "In Theory", 1991 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - TNG: "Half a Life", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - TNG: "The Mind's Eye", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - TNG: "Redemption", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - TNG: "Darmok", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - TNG: "Ensign Ro", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - TNG: "Unification Part II", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - TNG: "Disaster", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - TNG: "The Masterpiece Society", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - TNG: "Power Play", 1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - TNG: "The First Duty", 1992 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - TNG: "The Perfect Mate", 1992 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - TNG: "All Good Things", 1994 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 1.2: Star Trek: Deep Space Nine, circa 1993-1997; 1997
    - DS9: "The Siege", 1993 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - DS9: "Call to Arms", circa 1997 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Also contains contemporaneous material on Star Trek: Voyager as grouped together by Dan Curry.
    - DS9: "Sacrifice of Angels", circa 1997 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 1.3: Star Trek: Voyager, circa 1994 - 2000
    - VOY: "Caretaker", circa 1994 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - VOY: "Innocence", 1995 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - VOY: "Workforce", 2000 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - VOY: Images of Voyager and Defiant (photocopies), undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 1.4: Star Trek: Enterprise, circa 2001-2004
    - ENT: "Broken Bow", 2001 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - ENT: "Impulse", circa 2004 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Consists of an application for an unspecified award for "Impulse" in the category of "Outstanding Visual Effects in a Television Series."
- Series 2: Star Trek VHS Tapes, circa 1967-2005; 1987-1992
  Contains 90 VHS tapes of various Star Trek episodes as broadcast, office copies, element reels, comp reels, work prints, and other recorded material pertaining to the making and visual effects of Star Trek. Also includes a small amount of accompanying notes.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  - Star Trek: The Original Series, 1967 (Box 13)
    Contains one tape of an episode titled "The Trouble with Tribbles."
  - Star Trek: The Next Generation, circa 1987-1993 (Box 13, Box 14, Box 15)
    Contains sixty-four tapes. Includes a copy of the episode of TNG that Dan Curry directed, "Birthright, pt. 2," as broadcast in March 1993.
  - Star Trek: Voyager, 1994-1999 (Box 15)
    Contains six tapes. One tape titled "Director's Raw Material For Reel" contains clips from Star Trek TNG, DS9, and Voyager.
  - Star Trek: Enterprise, 2002-2005 (Box 15)
    Contains sixteen tapes.
  - Assorted Recordings, undated (Box 15)
    Contains two tapes containing Main Title Design Emmy submissions, and one tape titled "Creature Comforts."
  - VHS Tape Notes, circa 1991, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Contains copies of notes found with two VHS tapes: "DRE #9 Cloud Tank" ("Dan & Ron Element Reel," 1993) and "Star Trek TNG #205 Smoke (Dry Ice) DRE-007 W/Window" (1991).
- Series 3: Motion Picture Projects, circa 1988-1992
  Contains Curry's work on title and logo design, collected scripts and screenplays (some annotated and hand-drawn by Curry), correspondence, and personal notes pertaining to assorted motion picture and television projects. Materials for Thunder Strike and Stroke of Midnite (both unproduced), Moe's World, and The Truman Show were collected by Curry, but do not evidence any participation in the production of these projects.
  - Hot to Trot, circa 1988 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - The Blob, circa 1988 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - Hometown Films Logo, circa 1988 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Thunder Strike, circa 1990 (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
  - Moe's World, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Moe's World is a made-for-television movie.
  - Stroke of Midnite, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - The Truman Show, circa 1991 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Cool World, circa 1992 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: The American Film Institute, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Series 4: Television Projects, 1990-2008
  Contains one script and screenplays for The Flash, collected by – though not explicitly linked to – Dan Curry. Also contains hand-drawn screenplays for Chuck, for which Curry was visual effects supervisor.
  - The Flash, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Chuck, 2008 (Box 12, Folder 4)